End Story
Sodachi Riddle
Part Two
End Story
Sodachi Riddle
Part Two
Five Years Ago
Five years ago.
五年前
What sort of person was Araragi Koyomi back then,
in his first year of middle school?
つまり 中学一年生だった頃の
阿良々木暦が どういう奴だったかと言うと
まっすぐで 純粋で ひたむきな
He was honest, genuine, and motivated.
言うならば普通の子供だった
For all intents and purposes, he was a normal child.
凡庸(ぼんよう)なる阿良々木少年に
それでも何らかの特殊性を見いだすとするのならば
If we were to seek something uncommon in one so common,
それは彼の両親が
正義と平和と安全を旨(むね)とする警察官だったことだろう
it would be that his parents were policemen and his personality was heavily influenced
彼らの影響下で 僕という人格は育成された
by justice, peace, and security.
阿良々木少年は そういう意味では
比較的正義感の強い少年だった
You might say he was a boy with an unusually strong sense of justice.
五年前の話
Now, five years ago.
When the first term was ending, he grew a little restless.
一学期が終わろうという頃の彼は少し焦っていた
Not just a little.
少しじゃないな
かなり焦っていたかもしれない
Actually, it was a lot.
He had just gotten back the grades on his finals, and was disappointed in the results.
それというのも 先頃返却された期末試験の結果が
あまり思わしくなかったのである
特に数学だ
Especially in mathematics.
このままではまずいと思った
He couldn't accept it.
このままでは正しさが貫けないと彼は思った
Being on the right side of history was on the line.
Not being right in his studies was a source of embarrassment greater than the bad grade for him.
"学ぶ"という正しさが全うできなくなることは
彼にとっては数字以上に恥ずかしいことだった
End Story
Sodachi Riddle
I've always known
that words are lies
Quickly we forget
that which is vague and unclear
by escaping into a realm of magic
which stifles truth
During a sunless summer
I derived
the answer alone
The answer was you
I found an answer
that I thought was more correct
than anybody else
当時の僕はモンティ・ホール問題を知ってはいなかったけれど
Back then, I didn't know anything about the Monty Hall problem,
There is nothing in envelope b.
Do you want to switch your selection to envelope c?
but suddenly being confronted with it piqued my curiosity.
いきなり突きつけられたその問題に
興味をそそられた
I see you made it here,
Araragi.
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
You must have solved
the puzzle in the letter,
then?
No...
解けて...
I didn't solve it.
解けて ない
I changed my selection, but I don't know why c is correct.
選択は変更したけれど
どうして "ｃ" が正解なのかは わからない
I see.
Then let's begin by
solving it formally.
Come inside, Araragi.
Let's study.
Let us hone our intelligence.
Sodachi Riddle
本人の話によれば
他にも何人か手紙を出した相手はいたらしい
She said she gave the same letters to a few others,
but I was the only one who came to this run-down house to meet her.
だけどその手紙を受けて 廃屋という待ち合わせ場所にやってきたのは
僕だけだったそうだ
Without even knowing what you were getting into.
のこのことやってきたのは
のこのこと... まあ のこのことだよ
Without... Yes, I suppose.
l
s
i
u
a
e
o
I
d
c
y
.
u
s
r
o
n
e
Y
t
d
a
n
v
g
e
l
s
i
u
a
e
o
I
d
c
y
.
u
s
r
o
n
e
Y
t
d
a
n
v
g
e
l
s
i
u
a
e
o
I
d
c
y
.
u
s
r
o
n
e
Y
t
d
a
n
v
g
e
l
s
i
u
a
e
o
I
d
c
y
.
u
s
r
o
n
e
Y
t
d
a
n
v
g
e
l
s
i
u
a
e
o
I
d
c
y
.
u
s
r
o
n
e
Y
t
d
a
n
v
g
e
l
s
i
u
a
e
o
I
d
c
y
.
u
s
r
o
n
e
Y
t
d
a
n
v
g
e
l
s
i
u
a
e
o
I
d
c
y
.
u
s
r
o
n
e
Y
t
d
a
n
v
g
e
l
s
i
u
a
e
o
I
d
c
y
.
u
s
r
o
n
e
Y
t
d
a
n
v
g
e
l
s
i
u
a
e
o
I
d
c
y
.
u
s
r
o
n
e
Y
t
d
a
n
v
g
e
l
s
i
u
a
e
o
I
d
c
y
.
u
s
r
o
n
e
Y
t
d
a
n
v
g
e
l
s
i
u
a
e
o
I
d
c
y
.
u
s
r
o
n
e
Y
t
d
a
n
v
g
e
l
s
i
u
a
e
o
I
d
c
y
.
u
s
r
o
n
e
Y
t
d
a
n
v
g
e
l
s
i
u
a
e
o
I
d
c
y
.
u
s
r
o
n
e
Y
t
d
a
n
v
g
e
l
s
i
u
a
e
o
I
d
c
y
.
u
s
r
o
n
e
Y
t
d
a
n
v
g
e
l
s
i
u
a
e
o
I
d
c
y
.
u
s
r
o
n
e
Y
t
d
a
n
v
g
e
l
s
i
u
a
e
o
I
d
c
y
.
u
s
r
o
n
e
Y
t
d
a
n
v
g
e
l
s
i
u
a
e
o
I
d
c
y
.
u
s
r
o
n
e
Y
t
d
a
n
v
g
e
l
s
i
u
a
e
o
I
d
c
y
.
u
s
r
o
n
e
Y
t
d
a
n
v
g
e
That summer is what likely prevented me from being bad at math or hating it.
少なくともあのひと夏がなければ 僕は数学が苦手になっていただろうし
数学が嫌いになっていただろう
直江津高校に入ることもできなかったんじゃないのかな
I probably wouldn't have been able to get into Naoetsu High School.
ともあれ 物語の続きを聞きましょうか
Please continue your story, Araragi.
阿良々木先輩のひと夏のアバンチュールを
I want to know more about your summer adventure.
謎の少女と阿良々木先輩の 密会の続きを
About your secret meeting with the mystery girl.
Sodachi Riddle
というわけで これを モンティ・ホール問題って言うんだよ
So, this is called a Monty Hall problem.
面白いな!
That's so interesting!
もっとないのか こういう問題!
Are there more problems like this?
あるよ いっぱい
Sure, tons!
いくらでも教えてあげる
I'll teach them all to you.
I really hope you'll fall in love with math, and that you won't stop loving it.
阿良々木くんが数学のことを もっと好きになってくれるなら
数学を好きでい続けてくれるなら
I will love it!
僕 好きになるよ
数学を好きで居続ける
I won't stop loving it!
Let's study here again tomorrow!
じゃあ 明日からここで 一緒に勉強 し続けよう
Sodachi Riddle
From the end of the first term to the end of the summer holidays,
そして 一学期の末から 夏休みの終わりまで
I kept coming to this desolate house.
僕はずっと この廃屋に通い続けたんだ
謎の少女と勉強をし続けた
I kept studying with the mystery girl.
End Story 1      Sodachi Riddle Part Two
Black
人類史上もっとも美しい式 オイラーの等式についても
教えてくれたのは彼女だった
She was also the one who taught me about the most beautiful expression in human history: Euler's identity.
Even after all these years, I can recall a lot of formulas that're useless in school off the top of my head.
今でも僕はそれらの 言うなら学校では役には立たない”数学”を
そらで言うことができる
だから僕としては
あまり勉強していたって感じじゃなくて
It never really felt like studying to me.
ただ毎日 この廃屋に遊びに来ていたって感じでもあるんだが
I guess it was more like I went to this ruin to hang out.
End Story 1      Sodachi Riddle Part Two
Black
言うならここは 僕とその子の秘密基地みたいなものだったんだ
This was like our secret base, hers and mine.
いや 秘密塾と言うべきかな
A secret, personal cram school.
塾ねえ
Cram school, huh?
She insisted on this place.
あの子は この場所にこだわった
ここでしか勉強はしないって言った
She said she'd only meet me here.
End Story 1      Sodachi Riddle Part Two
Black
That was what she said when we met the next day in the chaos.
翌日 廃屋の部屋で集合した際
彼女はそう宣言したのだ
この勉強会を続けるための条件である
It was a condition she had.
条件を三つ
One of three conditions.
そのうちひとつが 勉強会の場所はここ
One, this is where we meet.
この廃屋の 二階の一番奥の部屋であることだった
In this run-down house, on the second floor at the very end.
End Story 1      Sodachi Riddle Part Two
Black
The second condition was that I would keep our study sessions a secret.
二つ目の条件は ここでそういう勉強会をしていることは
二人だけの秘密にするってこと 誰にも言わないこと
そして三つ目の条件は
And the third condition...
End Story 1      Sodachi Riddle Part Two
Black
私の名前を訊かないこと
Don't ask me my name.
私が誰なのかを探らないこと
Don't probe into my life.
数学のこと以外で 私に何も訊かないこと
Ask me only about math.
End Story 1      Sodachi Riddle Part Two
Black
Those three.
だった
She sounds like a math fairy.
数学の妖精か何かですか その子は
However, those three were the only things she demanded.
でも 逆に言えば それ以外のことはあの子は
何も要求しなかったんだ
End Story 1      Sodachi Riddle Part Two
Black
Nothing else at all.
本当に何も
Her three conditions and the initial request.
三つの条件と
それから最初に言ったお願いと
あまりに一方的に教えてもらってばかりなのが心苦しくて
僕はある日 お菓子を持って来たことがあったんだけどな
I felt bad just being taught all the time and giving nothing back, so I brought candy one day.
I'm not looking for compensation.
見返りが欲しくてやっているんじゃないの
私はあなたに数学を教えられて幸せ
I'm just happy to teach you math.
だからお願い
Please!
数学をずっと 愛し続けてね
Stay in love with math.
End Story 1      Sodachi Riddle Part Two
Black
Yep.
って
She sounds even more like a math fairy now.
ますます数学の妖精じみてきましたね
ともかく僕は彼女の出した条件を全部呑んで
それから毎日 この廃屋に通い詰めた
I accepted all her conditions and came here every day.
完全に毎日ですか?
Every single day?
一日も欠かさず?
Without fail?
でも その勉強会は
ある日突然 終わったから
But one day, it was suddenly over.
End Story 1      Sodachi Riddle Part Two
Black
夏休み最後の日のことだ
It was on the last day of the summer holidays.
Sodachi Riddle
いつだって先にそこにいて
勉強会の準備を済ませている少女が
Normally she would have already been there,
preparing our study session,
その日に限っては 来ていなかった
but she wasn't there that day.
End Story 1      Sodachi Riddle Part Two
White
For the first and only time,
その日に限って その日初めて
no matter how long I waited,
いつまでたっても いつまで待っても
彼女は現れなかった
she did not appear.
An envelope?
Araragi Koyomi realized, deep down,
なんとなく中学一年生の阿良々木暦は思った
もう僕は
that he wouldn't
ever learn math from her again here.
ここで彼女から"数学"を学ぶことはないのだろうと
He went to the other classes to find out who she was.
僕は 彼女の正体を探ろうと
他のクラスへと調査に乗り出したのだ
He found that the girl he met over the summer was neither in his grade nor in the grades above him.
しかし 同学年はもちろん 上級生にも
僕がひと夏の間 ずっと会っていた少女はいなかった
まるで存在ごと消えてしまったかのような彼女に
At the thought of her vanishing along with every trace of her existence,
阿良々木少年は そう,おののいた
the boy Araragi trembled.
He was scared.
怖い
初めてそのとき 彼女を怖いと思ったのだろう
For the first time, he was afraid of her.
だから 彼は廃屋に近づかなくなり
That's why he didn't go back to that ruin of a house.
That's why he forgot her.
だから 彼は少女のことを忘れた
だけど 廃屋で少女から学んだ数学のことだけは忘れず
However, he never forgot the math she taught him,
そして二学期以降 阿良々木少年の成績は
数学を中心に持ち直したのだった
and starting with the second term his grades recovered with math as the core.
つまりある意味 彼の生活は廃屋通いをする以前の
元の状態に戻ったというだけのことなのかもしれないが
While his daily life merely returned to the way it was before he went to that derelict house,
長い目で見れば何も変わっていないのかもしれないが
and while one less discerning
might think nothing changed at all,
しかし 確かに変わったと思えることもひとつあった
one thing changed without doubt.
阿良々木少年は概ね
その後も正しさを求める姿勢を貫いたけれど
He kept on having strong opinions on being in the right,
and from time to time this would lead to violence and conflict,
そのせいで時に暴走し
とんだしっぺ返しを食らうこともあったけれど
数学に限ってだけ言えば
彼は面白さを求めていたということだ
but at least he could find enjoyment in numbers.
そのよりどころがなければ
きっとあの学級会の際 正しさを打ち砕かれたあとに
If this had never happened,
he surely would have had nothing left in his heart
Private Naoetsu High School
彼の心にはきっと
何も残らなかったことだろう
after the class meeting that destroyed his sense of justice.
あの子が数学の面白さを
She taught him that numbers were fun.
人生の面白さを
She taught him that life was fun.
She taught him that the world was fun.
世界の面白さを教えてくれたから
It's what makes me who I am now.
今の僕がある
僕はあの夏でできていた
That summer is the fabric of my personality.
Sodachi Riddle
え でも要するにその謎の少女が老倉先輩なんですよね?
So, the mystery girl was Oikura, right?
いやいや阿良々木先輩
Come on, Araragi.
謎解きってほどじゃあないでしょう これは
This didn't even require a master detective.
むしろこの流れで その子が老倉さんじゃなかったら
いささかミスディレクションが過ぎると言うものです
If she hadn't been Oikura, we would have wasted all this time on a red herring.
アンフェアだって言われちゃいますよ
Is that really fair?
じゃあ 扇ちゃん
All right, Ougi.
夏休み明け その子が 少女老倉が
How do you explain that this girl, the young Oikura Sodachi,
七百一中学校にいなかったことは どう説明する?
wasn't in Nanahyakuichi Middle School
when summer was over?
転校したんです
She transferred schools.
ただしこの推測にはひとつだけ穴がありますよね
I admit this conjecture has a hole in it.
It means that you and she were in the same grade once.
即ち老倉先輩と阿良々木先輩が
かつて同級生だったということになるからです
However, the way you phrased things so far
implied that you only ever met her in high school.
阿良々木先輩のこれまでの口振りでは 直江津高校に入学して初めて
阿良々木先輩は老倉先輩と会ったかのようでしたが?
Because I thought I had.
初めて会ったと思ったんだよ 僕は
つまり完全に
僕は少女老倉のことを忘れていたということだ
I forgot that I'd ever met her when we were younger.
I forgot why I became good at math,
自分が誰のお陰で 数学が得意なのかも忘れて
forgot everything I owed her,
どれくらいあいつに恩義があるのかも忘れて
and treated her like a normal classmate.
僕はクラスメイトとしてあいつに接していたんだ
She said I have mathematics to thank for everything I am today,
今の僕があるのは
全部数学のお陰だってあいつは言っていた
戦場ヶ原と付き合っていることさえ
even that Senjougahara is my girlfriend.
だけどそれは 本当は
私のお陰だって言いたかったのか
Perhaps she was trying to say that it was all thanks to her.
"I love happy people, but I hate those that
don't understand why they're happy," huh?
幸せな奴は好きだけれど
自分が幸せな理由を知らない奴が嫌い ですか
End Story 1      Sodachi Riddle Part Two
Red
Black
Hate
End Story 1      Sodachi Riddle Part Two
Red
そしてなんでしたっけ
What was the other thing?
自分が何でできているか知らない奴が嫌い?
"I hate the ones that don't know
what makes them who they are?"
ふふ 実際に忘れていた記憶を思い出してしてみると
含蓄(がんちく)のある言葉ですね
Now that you remember what you forgot, those words cut deep, don't they?
とにかく...
Anyway...
明日 僕は老倉に謝らなきゃな
I have to apologize to her tomorrow.
それであいつが嫌っている僕を好きになってくれるわけもないだろうし
I doubt that it'll result in a sudden outburst of friendliness,
あいつの何かを楽にしてやれるわけでもないんだろうが
and perhaps it won't make anything easier for her,
but I still feel like I have to do it.
謝るべきなんだから 謝るべきだ
おや あまり気が進まなそうですね
You don't seem to like the thought.
そりゃあな
Yeah...
僕のほうから言いたい文句だって
ないわけじゃないんだぜ?
Y'know, I can be rightfully upset about a bunch of things myself.
Why didn't she tell me she was going to transfer schools?
転校とか まあそういう事情があったにしても
去る前に一言言ってくれてもよかったじゃないか
How am I supposed to understand an empty envelope?
あんな空っぽの封筒だけ残されても
わけわかんねーよ
Oikura Sodachi
Besides, all she had to do was remind me about it when we met again later, and I would have remembered.
それに 一年三組で再会したとき
その場で言ってくれたら その場で思い出せたはずなんだ
今になって言われても
Getting upset now is unreasonable.
ふふ その場で言ってくれたら ねえ?
Remind you, huh?
That girl was me, Araragi.
あのときの少女は私だよ 阿良々木くん
Long time no see!
久しぶりい
なぁに 私のこと忘れちゃったの?
Aw, you forgot me?
You're awwwful!
やだサイテー
もー 冷たいんだからー
Sniff...
でも そんなところが
But that's also...
ス・テ・キ☆
really sweeto
Is that what you're getting at here?
とか言ってくれたらという意味ですか?
Not a single character in this work
has been that magnanimous so far!
そんな壮絶なキャラは
この世界観でかつて見たことがないけれど
まあ...
But...
Then...
ならばあなたは
どうして彼女がそれを言わなかったかを考えるべきでしょう
Perhaps you should think hard about why she didn't tell you.
そして どうして彼女が別れを告げずに去っていったのか
それも考えなければなりません
And think also about why she left without saying farewell.
でないと 明日謝ったとしても
事態はより悪化するだけかもしれませんよ
Otherwise any apology tomorrow is likely to make it worse.
Nothing infuriates the victim like half-baked apologies.
口先だけの謝罪ほど
被害者を怒らせるものはありませんからね
The victim?
被害者?
おいおい ちょっと待ってくれよ 扇ちゃん
Hold on, Ougi.
Aren't you exaggerating?
それは言い過ぎじゃないのか?
そうですね
Perhaps, yes.
Of course it isn't actively your fault.
もちろん 阿良々木先輩が悪いわけではありません
ただ 阿良々木先輩は愚か者です
You're just a fool.
Always the fool.
どうしようもなく どうしようもない
扇ちゃん きみはいったい
何を知っていると言うんだい?
Ougi. What do you know?
私は何も知りませんよ
I know nothing.
You know everything, Araragi.
あなたが知っているんです 阿良々木先輩
僕―
I—
そうですね ここは老倉先輩の少女時代を見習って
クイズと洒落込みましょうか
Let me follow little Oikura's example and be the quizmaster.
問題です
Here is your question.
老倉育は阿良々木暦のことが親の仇のように嫌いです
Oikura Sodachi hates you as though you were her mortal enemy.
That's because you didn't live up to her expectations.
それは阿良々木暦が
老倉育の期待に応えてくれなかったからです
だから彼女は
彼に何も告げずに転校して行ったのです
That's why she transferred away without saying anything.
さて 老倉育は阿良々木暦に
いったい何を望んでいたのでしょうか?
Now, what did Oikura Sodachi expect of Araragi Koyomi?
何を 望んで?
What she expected?
Hint: It's related to your parents' occupation.
ヒント 阿良々木先輩のご両親の職業に関係があります
You have one hundred and twenty seconds.
シンキングタイム 百二十秒
Sodachi Riddle
Solution
Essentially, Oikura did expect compensation in return for teaching you that math is fun or whatever.
要するに老倉先輩は 阿良々木先輩に数学の
なんですか 面白さとやらを教えるのと引き替えに 見返りを求めていたということですよ
Compensation
第三者の立場から言わせてもらえれば
やっぱり最初の封筒って 怪しいですよね
Objectively, I must say that the first letter was already sketchy.
罠(わな)の臭いがぷんぷんします
It seems like it was a trap to me.
Trap
罠
A trap.
Trap
言うなら釣り針ですか
You took the bait.
That she sent letters to others and you were the only one who showed up was a lie.
他の生徒にも手紙を出していて
阿良々木先輩だけが現れたという本人の弁は嘘ですよ
まるっきりの虚言です
A big, fat lie.
She was always fishing only for you.
事実は阿良々木先輩だけを狙っての一本釣りでしょう
阿良々木先輩が数学の成績を落としているのを知った老倉先輩が
She knew that your math grades had slipped
そこにつけ込む形で
興味を引くであろう内容の封筒を下駄箱に入れたということでしょう
and seized the opportunity to place envelopes in your shoe locker that were likely to grab your attention.
教科数学をなんとかしなきゃと思っている少年のところに
数学的問題
Giving a student worried about his math grade a math problem...
まあ いい疑似餌(ぎじえ)ですよ
It was exceptional bait.
So when I showed up without knowing what I was getting into...
とすると 本当にのこのこと現れた僕って感じだが
Hey, Araragi.
ねえ阿良々木先輩
阿良々木先輩は 私の叔父さんであるところの忍野メメがこの町で暮らした
学習塾跡の廃墟を よくご存知なんですよね?
You know the derelict cram school that my uncle, Oshino Meme, was lodging in rather well, right?
Yeah. Like I said.
ん... ああ そりゃあ
言っただろ
僕自身 そこで寝泊まりしたこともあるくらいだって
I even crashed there.
And you also said this:
そしてあなたはこうも言いました
この廃屋とあの廃墟は同じくらいボロボロだと
言いましたよね?
This empty house and that ruin of a cram school are similarly run-down. Right?
言ったけど?
I did. So?
Don't you think that's weird?
それ おかしくないです?
なんで数年前に潰れたばかりの学習塾と
Why is a cram school that was
abandoned only a few years ago
五年前に既に廃屋だった民家とが
同じくらいボロボロなんですか?
equally as ruined as a house that
was already a ruin five years ago?
そうです 阿良々木先輩
Precisely, Araragi.
This wasn't a ruin five years ago.
五年前 ここは廃屋ではなかったんです
End Story 1      Sodachi Riddle Part Two
Black
廃屋というのはあなたの勘違いです
You mistook it for one.
This was where Oikura Sodachi lived.
ここは 老倉育の住まう家でした
Sodachi Riddle
Where she lived?
老倉の 住まう家?
Why was she always here before you?
どうして 彼女はいつも 阿良々木先輩よりも先に
ここに来ていたんです?
一度の例外もなく 待ち合わせ場所に先着していたなんて
おかしいと思いませんか?
Don't you think it's weird that she would invariably be first to meet you?
自宅だったからこそ 老倉先輩はここで常に
待ち構えることができたと見るべきです
She was waiting here for you because it was her home.
でも—
But—
Now, Araragi.
さて阿良々木先輩
ショックをお受けのところに鞭を打つようで申し訳ありませんが
私の推理はここからが肝要(かんよう)です
I'm loath to edge you on, shocked as you are,
but now we're getting to the heart of the matter.
どうして阿良々木先輩は五年前
老倉家を廃屋だと思ったのでしょう
Why, I wonder, did you think this was a ruin five years ago?
そりゃ 記憶違いってことだろう?
I must be misremembering.
No, you were mistaken.
いえ 勘違いです
記憶自体はたぶんあっていますよ
Your memories are probably accurate.
この部屋の窓は 既にこんな具合に割れていたと
具体的に証言されていたじゃあないですか
You said the windows were already broken in this room back then.
だから記憶違いではなく 勘違いなのです
You aren't misremembering. You were mistaken.
家庭内暴力って奴か
Domestic violence?
そうですね
Yes.
なかなか悲惨な家庭環境でお育ちになられたようですね 老倉さんは
What a wretched childhood Oikura must have had.
平和な家庭でぬくぬく育った阿良々木先輩が
You are surrounded by warmth and peace at home
この家に通い詰めたひと夏のことを
記憶の片隅に押し込んだとしても
and confined your time here to the furthest reaches of your memory.
記憶の奥底に押しまい込んだとしても
それは責められることではないのかもしれません
Perhaps you shouldn't even be blamed for that.
二学期になってからの転校の理由も
こうなるとなんとなく想像がつきますね
This also explains why she transferred schools when the second term began.
崩壊しつつあった家庭が
完全に崩壊したってことでしょう
Her family finally fell apart for good.
その際に老倉さんは名字が変わったのかもしれませんね?
Her surname must have changed.
だからこそ直江津高校一年三組で再会したときに
阿良々木先輩は初対面だと思った とか
I suppose that's the reason you thought you'd never met her before your time in class 1-3.
まあ顔でわかれって話ですけれどね
Well, I guess you should have recognized her.
ともあれ
Onward.
老倉家がその頃
極限状態にあったことは間違いないでしょう
There is little doubt that Oikura
faced extraordinary circumstances.
そして彼女はそれをなんとかしたかった
She wanted to change that.
なんとかって
Change how?
Somehow.
なんとかはなんとかです
だから阿良々木先輩を呼んだんですよ
That was why she invited you.
老倉先輩が阿良々木先輩に求めた見返りとは
つまりはそういうことだったんです
That was the compensation she desired of you.
Hold on.
いや ちょっと待てよ
家庭崩壊 暴力を伴う家庭崩壊の解決なんて
荷が重過ぎるだろ
How was I going to do something about the
violence and escalating discord of her family?
中学一年生に何を期待していたんだ
あいつは?
What did she expect of someone in his first year of middle school?
Not you. Your parents.
だからご両親ですよ
My parents...
両親...
They're cops, right?
警察官なんでしょう?
阿良々木先輩に正しさを示したご両親
Those parents who instilled such a strong sense of justice in you.
そのご両親に 老倉家の有様を報告することを
あなたは期待されていたんです
She wanted you to report everything you saw here to your parents.
End Story 1      Sodachi Riddle Part Two
Black
Then why did she make me promise I wouldn't tell anybody?
だとしても 口止めされていたんだけれど
僕は 老倉自身から
ここで老倉と会っていることを誰にも言うなって
I had to keep it a secret that we were even meeting.
あくまでも老倉先輩は
家族を自ら告発したくはなかったんでしょうよ
She didn't want to indict her own family.
娘として親を自ら咎める形になるのは気が咎めるのか
Perhaps she was reluctant to accuse her own parents.
End Story 1      Sodachi Riddle Part Two
White
それとも報復を恐れてのことなのか
Perhaps she was afraid of their punishment.
これも両方ですかねえ?
Both, probably.
She was hoping I would stand up and talk to my parents.
あくまで僕が自発的に 老倉家の様子を両親に告発するのを望んでいた
目論んでいたということか
End Story 1      Sodachi Riddle Part Two
Black
I didn't live up to her expectations,
僕は老倉が望んでいたことを何もしてやれず
その癖 老倉が僕に与えてくれた知識だけは
存分に吸収していったってわけだ
but I still sponged up all the knowledge that she fed me.
End Story 1      Sodachi Riddle Part Two
Black
老倉が卓袱台の裏に張り付けて行った空っぽの封筒こそが
僕という男を如実に表していた
The empty envelope that Oikura taped to the underside of the table was a metaphor of me.
Empty. Wrong door.
"空っぽ"で"外れ"
当てにならない男だった
I proved to be a waste of time.
End Story 1      Sodachi Riddle Part Two
Black
ふふふ ま おおよそこんなところですが
Yes, that seems just about right.
阿良々木先輩 私の記憶が確かならば
Araragi, if my memory serves me right,
確か阿良々木先輩は どうして自分が老倉先輩から
親の仇のように嫌われているのかを探るために 今回の調査を実施したはずだと思うのですが
we started this investigation to establish why
Oikura hates you like you were her mortal enemy.
We can regard the investigation as largely concluded now.
その目的は 現時刻をもって概ね達成できたと思われます
つきましてはそろそろ撤退を図るべき頃合いだと考えますけれど
最後に一言 何かありましたらどうぞ
I believe now would be the time to take our leave,
but you should be given time to say something as well.
締めの一言を
Your closing statement.
I am really blessed right now.
今の僕はとても恵まれているよ
確かに順風満帆で
My life really is smooth sailing.
幸せだ
I am happy.
友達がいて 恋人がいて 後輩がいて
I have friends, a girlfriend, people who rely on me.
とてもとても幸せだ
I am very, very happy.
だけど
But—
I've started hating myself a little for my happiness.
そんな幸せな僕を 僕は少し
嫌いになってしまったよ
ならばその分 私があなたを愛しましょう
Then I shall love you to even the score.
それに阿良々木先輩
And besides, Araragi.
考えようによっちゃあ
数学までを嫌いにならなくてよかったじゃないですか
Aren't you glad you haven't started hating math?
違いねえ
Damn right.
確かに
Yes.
何を嫌いになっても 正しさを見失っても
数学だけは愛し続ける
Whatever I hate, and despite losing my sense of what is right and just, I still love math.
By now it may very well be a sort of curse.
それはもはや 一種の呪いのようでもあった
Sodachi Riddle
Oshino Ougi?
忍野扇?
Oshino's niece?
忍野さんの 姪っ子?
Uh... Yeah.
その子のお陰で色々と判明してな
Lots of things have become clear to me thanks to her.
さすが忍野の係累(けいるい)というか
なかなかの名探偵ぶりだぜ
I suppose she shares his blood,
but she's like a detective or something.
Naoetsu Private High School
あの子がいなければ 昨日も一昨日も
謎は解けないままだっただろうな
Without her I never would've solved the mysteries yesterday and the day before.
阿良々木くん
Araragi.
今の阿良々木くんを これ以上追い詰めるようなことを言うのは
とても心苦しいんだけれど
Honestly, I don't want to pry into this any further,
阿良々木くんが 中学一年生の一学期の期末試験で
数学の壁にぶつかっていたことくらいなら 何らかの方法で知ってもおかしくはない
and it's perfectly plausible that she somehow found out you were about to fail math after the finals.
そこをつくように
モンティ・ホール問題を下駄箱に入れることもできると思う
She capitalized on that and put the
Monty Hall problem in your shoe locker.
でも その計画の肝(きも)である
阿良々木くんのご両親が警察官だってことを
But all this hinges on the knowledge that your parents are policemen.
老倉さんはどうやって知ったの?
How did she know that?
Usually it takes you a long time to tell that to people.
それは阿良々木くんが
ひたすらひた隠しにしていることじゃなかったっけ?
そうだ
Yes.
それについては僕は 余計な
あるいは不要なトラブルを避けるために
I made it a habit to never tell anybody of
my parents' profession, even when asked,
訊かれても言わない癖がついている
to avoid unnecessary problems.
なのにどうして
So, how?
どうして老倉はそれを知っていた?
How did she know?
どうやって?
How?
Well, I mean, she probably learned it by some sort of coincidence.
そりゃあもちろん 何かのきっかけで
たまたま知っていたってこともあるかもしれないけれど
まだ あるんじゃないのかな
Isn't there something else?
何か 阿良々木くんと老倉さんの間には
Something that connects you.
Something you need to recall.
何か 遡(さかのぼ)らなければならない記憶が
開けなければならない扉が
A door you need to open.
遡らなければならない記憶
Something I need to recall.
End Story 1      Sodachi Riddle Part Two
Black
開けなければならない扉
A door I need to open.
僕にはまだ 忘れていることがあるのだろうか
There's still something I've forgotten.
これ以上
Even now.
だとすれば
阿良々木暦は どこまで愚かなのだろうか
Just how foolish a man is Araragi Koyomi?
僕の愚かに 限りはないのか
Is there no limit to my foolishness?
私がお前のことを忘れるはずがないじゃない
"Do you think I could ever forget you?"
老倉はそう言っていた
Those were Oikura's words.
She undoubtedly remembers.
だとすれば 彼女はきっと覚えているのだ
She remembers what happened two years ago,
five years ago, and also what the fool did before that.
二年前の 五年前の そしてそれ以前の愚か者を
僕は教室の前に到着した
I arrived before the classroom.
この扉の向こうに老倉育がいるのかどうかは
さてもまったく不可能な証明だった
Whether or not Oikura Sodachi was beyond the door was entirely impossible to prove.
It was entirely impossible to prove.
I hear your laughter near me
You were supposed to be there forever
I breathed onto the classroom window and wrote your name
only to panic and wipe it with my sleeve
I heard your voice from the hallway
and went home in hurry to hide my feelings
At some point I became unable
to talk to you normally
I can hear your laughter a ways away
You were supposed to be next to me forever
You knew how I felt
even when I said nothing
Now I know how important you were to me,
but we will never see each other again